A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, National Affairs, Office Files of Robert H. Goldmann FA654
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, National Affairs, Office Files of Robert H. Goldmann
1968-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Goldmann, Robert, 1921-
Ford Foundation
FA654
9.6 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series by file type.
Series I. Subject Files, 1968-1982
Series II. Grant Files, 1974-1982
Series III. Reports and Project Evaluations, 1968-1981
Conditions Governing Access
Records are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Contains subject files, grant files, reports and project evaluations.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Goldmann (1921-2018) worked for more than ten years at the Ford Foundation. Goldmann was a Program Officer in the Foundation's Division of National Affairs from the late 1960s until the restructuring of the Foundation's programming in the early 1980s.
Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, Golmann had positions at Voice of America, the United States Department of State's Alliance for Progress, and New York City's Human Resources Administration. While at Voice of America, Goldmann started as a German language announcer and then became manager of the newsroom.
After leaving the Ford Foundation, Goldmann became European Director of the Anti-Defamation League and was based in Paris, France.
Born in Reinheim, Germany, Goldmann moved to the United States in 1939. He attended Columbia University where he studied Spanish and journalism.
- Subject Files, 1968-1982; I
  - Administration and Program Operations -- Ford Foundation Library Periodicals, Grant Guidelines, Staff Rosters, Personnel Policies, etc., 1976-1981 (Box 1)
  - Communications -- General -- Communications Task Force, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Communications -- General -- Investigative Reporting Project -- Alfred W. Balk, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Communications -- General -- Grants, Possible Media Projects, National Press Council, American Broadcasting, etc., 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Community Development Corporations -- Report (draft c. 1973/1974?), undated (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- November 27, 1977 Meeting, 1977 November 27 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- November 29, 1977 Meeting, 1977 November 29 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- December 9, 1977 Meeting, 1977 December 9 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- 1977 Meeting Materials (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- Case Studies (folder 1) -- Gillers, "Fact Finding in Forest Hills", 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- Case Studies (folder 1) -- Gillers, Dispute Resolution in Prison: The California Experience", 1978 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- Case Studies (folder 2) -- Kwartler, Richard -- Consultancy Memoranda and Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- Case Studies (folder 2) -- Kwartler, Richard, "The Snoqualmie River Conflict", 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- Case Studies (folder 2) -- Kwartler, Richard, "This is Our Land: The Mohawk Indians vs. the State of New York", 1978 June (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- Case Studies (folder 2) -- Fleishman, Joel, "Not Without Honor: A Prophet Even in his Own Country" Re: St. Louis Public Housing Tenant Strike of 1969, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Conflict Resolution -- General, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - "Conflict Resolution and Regulation - Another Look" and Appendix -- Information Paper, 1977 September (Box 1)
  - Consultancy Agreements, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshops on Ethnic Conflict (Kenya and Sri Lanka), 1981 (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshops on Ethnic Conflict -- Goldmann -- Pre-Workshop Memoranda, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshop on Structural Arrangements to Ease Ethnic Tensions, Taita Hills, Kenya -- Memoranda, Papers, Reports, Speech (folder 1), 1981 September 21-25 (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshop on Structural Arrangements to Ease Ethnic Tensions, Taita Hills, Kenya -- Memoranda, Papers, Reports, Speech (folder 2), 1981 September 21-25 (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshop on Structural Arrangements to Ease Ethnic Tensions, Taita Hills, Kenya -- Memoranda, Papers, Reports, Speech (folder 3), 1981 September 21-25 (Box 8)
  - Cross National Workshop on Structural Arrangements to Ease Ethnic Tensions, Taita Hills, Kenya -- Summary of Highlights, 1981 October 7 (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshop on Structural Arrangements to Ease Ethnic Tensions, Taita Hills, Kenya -- Evaluations, Follow-Up, 1981 September 21-25 (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshop on Structural Arrangements to Ease Ethnic Tensions, Taita Hills, Kenya -- Reports, Planning Materials, etc., 1981 September (Box 1)
  - Cross National Workshop -- Discussion Results -- Proposal for Centre for Comparative Ethnic Studies in Sri Lanka, 1981 December 29 (Box 2)
  - Cross National Workshop on Ethnic Conflict Resolution (2nd), Sri Lanka -- Correspondence with Participants Re: Papers and Workshop, 1981 June-1982 February (Box 2)
  - Cross National Workshop on Ethnic Conflict Resolution (2nd), Sri Lanka -- Agenda, Session Plan, Memoranda Re: Follow-Up Activities, 1982 March 6-14 (Box 2)
  - Ethnic Conflict -- Africa, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Ethnic Conflict -- DAP, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Ethnic Conflict -- Developing Countries -- Report, Memoranda, Notes (handwritten), 1980 (Box 2)
  - Ethnic Conflict -- Visit to Malaysia, Philippines; Development Issues, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Heffner, Richard -- Video Re: Environmental Issues, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict (proportionalism) -- Goldmann Memorandum Re; Ford Foundation's Future and Emphasis on Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict, 1976 October 5 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict (proportionalism) -- November 7, 1978 Meeting, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- General -- Donald Horowitz Consultancy -- Ethnic Conflict Studies, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- General -- Robert Goldmann Memorandum, "Next Steps" Re: Ethnic Conflict and Achieving Minorities, 1977 November 15 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- General -- Memoranda, Reports Re: Ethnic Conflic in the Developing World, Community Development, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- Case Studies, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- Reports -- "Human Rights and Intellectual Freedom" by David Heaps, 1975 November (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- Reports -- "Achieving Minorities and Ethnic Conflict" by Donald L. Horowitz, 1977 July (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- Reports -- "Ethnic Conflict: Designing a Research Program" by Donald L. Horowitz, 1978 August (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- Reports -- "Ethnic Conflict: Focusing the Research Program" by Donald L. Horowitz, 1978 December (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- Reports -- "Structural Techniques to Reduce Ethnic Conflict" by Donald L. Horowitz, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Human Rights and Ethnic Conflict -- Reports -- "Ethnic Conflict Policy Studies - A Concept Paper" by Donald L. Horowitz, undated (Box 2)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) -- Material for April 18, 1980 Board of Directors Meeting, 1980 April 18 (Box 2)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) -- Grant for 5 Year National Supported Work Demonstration for the Mentally Retarded, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Media -- Seminar, "The Citizen and the News" (St. Petersburg, Florida), 1979 (Box 2)
  - Media and Politics in Germany, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - National Affairs -- Grants Accounting -- Lists, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - National Affairs Grants -- Quarterly Grant Breakdown for Board of Trustees Meeting (folder 1), 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - National Affairs Grants -- Quarterly Grant Breakdown for Board of Trustees Meeting (folder 2), 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - National Affairs Division -- Office of the Vice President -- Consultants -- Lists and Memo Re: General Terms and Entitlements, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Project Equality (folder 1), 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - Project Equality (folder 2), 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - Project Equality -- Ford Foundation Proposal (folder 3), 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - Public Agenda Foundation -- Unemployment (folder 1), 1976 (Box 3)
  - Public Agenda Foundation -- Unemployment (folder 2), 1976 (Box 3)
  - Record of Reports, Correspondence and List of Documents Sent to/from WCP -- Administrative File, circa 1980 (Box 3)
- Grant Files, 1974-1982; II
  - Grants -- General, 1981 (Box 3)
  - American Assembly (#785-0245) -- Proposal, Approval, Pink Form, 1978 (Box 3)
  - American Assembly, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Brookings Institution (#770-0287) -- Steven Hess -- Correspondence, Reports, 1975-1978 (Box 3)
  - Brookings Institution (#765-0297 and #770-0287) -- Pink Form, RGA's, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - Brookings Institution -- Steven Hess -- Study of Washington Newsgathering -- Report, Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Corporation for Public-Private Ventures, 1978-1982 (Box 4)
  - Corporation for Public-Private Ventures, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Council for International Urban Liaison (January-December 1980) (Box 4)
  - Council for International Urban Liaison, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Criminal Justice Publications, Inc., 1977-1981 (Box 4)
  - Criminal Justice Publications, Inc. ($300,000), 1981 (Box 4)
  - Criminal Justice Publications, Inc. ($10,000), 1981 (Box 4)
  - Curvin and Porter -- "Looting Report" and Related Correspondence, Memoranda, 1977-1979 (Box 4)
  - DAPs -- General -- DAP769-0803 -- Conflict Resolution (October 1, 1980-September 31, 1981), 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - DAPs -- General -- DAP769-0803B -- Conflict Resolution -- RGA, Pink Form, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - DAPs -- General -- DAP769-0803C -- Conflict Resolution (April 1, 1979-March 31, 1980), 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - DAPs -- General -- DAP749-0810 -- To Undertake Research and Demonstration Efforts in the Field of Employment and Social Policy, 1977-1981 (Box 4)
  - DAPs -- General -- DAP749-0819 -- Media and the Political Process, Incl. Office of Public Broadcasting Report Re: Communications Program, 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - DAPs -- General -- Cross National Workshops I and II, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Duke University -- David Barber Correspondence Re: Media and Politics, Campaigning, 1975-1979 (Box 4)
  - Duke University (#750-0253, #750-0253A/B) -- Pink Forms, RGAs, Modifications, 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Federation of Jewish Philanthropies (#785-0121), 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Institute for Mediation and Conflict Resolution, 1981 (Box 4)
  - MIT -- Grant Re: Proposition 2 1/2 and Improving Government Performance, 1981 (Box 4)
  - National Governors Association, 1981 (Box 4)
  - National Governors Association -- Demonstration of Double Social Utility, 1980 (Box 4)
  - National Governors Association -- Double Social Utility Demonstration -- Final Report and Proposal, Appendices, 1980 May (Box 4)
  - National Governors Association -- Working File, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - National Judicial College, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - National Judicial College, 1981 (Box 4)
  - National Opinions Research Center (August 1981-July 31, 1982), 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - New School -- Support for Completion of a Book on Welfare by Blanch Bernstein (May 1, 1981-December 31, 1981) (Box 4)
  - Transitional Employment Enterprises, Inc. -- Site Visits Memorandum, 1979 October 16 (Box 4)
  - University of Zurich (#760-0485) -- Correspondence, 1975 (Box 4)
  - University of Zurich (#760-0485) -- RGA, Pink Form, Modifications, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Urban Institute, 1981 (Box 4)
  - University of Zurich (#760-0485A) -- RGA, Pink Form, Grant Letter, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
- Reports and Project Evaluations, 1968-1981; III
  - Brody, Ralph -- "Project Bridge - An Assessment of a Program to Improve Black-White Relations in Cleveland, Ohio", 1969 August (Box 5)
  - Brooks, Richard and Judith Rubenstein -- "The National Council on Crime and Delinquency...", 1969 August (Box 5)
  - Brooks, Rubenstein -- National Council on Crime and Delinquency -- Evaluation Drafts, 1969 August (Box 5)
  - Cahn, Robert -- "The Land Savers - A Report on the Nature Conservancy", 1969 June-July (Box 5)
  - Clemow, Bice --"The Center for Research and Education in American Liberties at Columbia University Teachers College", 1969 August (Box 5)
  - Cochran, Robert -- "From Hope to Crisis - An Assessment of the Open Space Action Institute", 1969 May (Box 5)
  - Cochran, Robert -- "From Hope to Crisis - An Assessment of the Open Space Action Institute" -- Draft, 1969 May (Box 5)
  - Giesey, Walter -- "Open America - An Assessment of the Work of the National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing (NCDH)", 1969 September (Box 5)
  - Goldmann, Robert -- "Where Next in the Delta?" Re: Research and Development Corporation Project at the Greenville Air Force Base, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Goldmann, Robert -- "Performance in Black and White - An Appraisal of the Development and Record of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration and Development and Services Corporations" (folder 1), 1969 February (Box 5)
  - Goldmann, Robert -- "Performance in Black and White - An Appraisal of the Development and Record of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration and Development and Services Corporations" (folder 2, slightly different copy), 1969 February (Box 5)
  - Gordon, Mitchell -- "Organized Labor and Organized Communities - The Watts Labor Community Action Committeee - Prototype for Community Unions?", 1969 August (Box 5)
  - Gordon, Mitchell -- "Organized Labor and Organized Communities" -- Draft, 1969 July-August (Box 5)
  - Gordon, Mitchell -- "The Unsettled Settlement House - An Evaluation of the Westminster Neighborhood Association, Inc. (in Watts), 1969 August (Box 5)
  - Kramer, Herbert J. -- "The 'Riessman Operation' - An Evaluation of the Ford Foundation's Grant to the New Careers Development Center", 1969 (Box 5)
  - Levin, Betsy -- "And Then, There Were the Children... An Assessment of Efforts to Test Decentralization in New York City's Public School System" -- Original Manuscript, 1969 May (Box 5)
  - Levin, Betsy -- "And Then, There Were the Children..." (with assistance from Ruth Turner Perot), 1969 May (Box 5)
  - Levin, Betsy -- "And Then, There Were the Children..." Annex, 1969 July (Box 5)
  - Levin, Betsy -- Additions and Corrections to Decentralization Evaluation Report, 1969 May 23 (Box 6)
  - Levin, Betsy -- "And Then, There Were the Children..." Three Demonstration Schools -- Drafts, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Kruger, Levin, Morris -- School Decentralization -- 201, 39, etc., 1969 (Box 6)
  - Levin, Talbott -- Decentralization, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Michalak, Joseph -- "SCOPE and U.P.A. - Two Efforts to Bring Parents Closer to Schools", 1969 April (Box 6)
  - Michalak, Joseph -- "SCOPE and U.P.A. - Two Efforts to Bring Parents Closer to Schools" -- Draft, 1969 April (Box 6)
  - Morris, Barbara and Ronald Davenport -- "Mission Accomplished, But Lessons to be Learned - An Evaluation of the Ford Foundation Grant to the Howard University School of Law", 1969 June (Box 6)
  - Newman, Jon -- "Verifying VERA - A Criminal Justice Coordinating Council for Cleveland", 1969 September (Box 6)
  - Norwitch, Bernard -- "Trying to Improve the State of the States - An Evaluation of the Citizens' Conference on State Legislatures", 1969 July (Box 6)
  - Norwitch, Bernard -- "Trying to Improve the State of the States - An Evaluation of the Citizens' Conference on State Legislatures" -- Draft, 1969 June (Box 6)
  - Norwitch, Bernard -- Evaluation of Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Passett, Barry, Bryant George and Starry Krueger -- "Generation Gap on a Southern Island" Re: Penn Community Center, 1969 September (Box 6)
  - Passett, Barry and Starry Krueger -- "Ministers and Cities - An Assessment of the Urban Training Center for Christian Missions", 1969 September (Box 6)
  - Schiff, Bennett -- "Unions and the Urban Crisis - A Report on the Work of the Union-University Urban Affairs Program", 1969 (Box 6)
  - Schrank, Robert -- "American Society for Training and Development, Los Angeles Chapter", 1969 January-February (Box 6)
  - Sylvester, Edward ad Raymond Mack -- "Pattern for Social Change - An Evaluation of the MARC Fellowship/Internship Program", 1969 August (Box 6)
  - Sylvester, Edward and Lisle Carter -- "Cleveland Core-Target City - An Assessment of the Foundation's Grants to the CORE Special Purpose Fund", 1969 (Box 6)
  - Cohen, Henry -- "Time to Re-think the Strategy" Re: Non-Profit Housing Center of the Urban Coalition, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Goldmann, Robert -- "The Lessons of a Year - Discussion Paper on Project Evaluation", 1970 February (Box 7)
  - Laue, James H. and Susan Macovsky -- "Third Men in New Arenas of Conflict" Re: National Center for Dispute Settlement (American Arbitration Association) and Racial Negotiations Project, 1970 November (Box 7)
  - Laue, James H. and Susan Macovsky -- "Third Men in New Arenas of Conflict" (folder 2), 1970 (Box 7)
  - Seessel, Thomas -- "Three Experiments in Shared Philanthropy" Re: The Kansas City Association of Trusts and Foundations, the Cleveland Foundation, and the University of Texas Hogg Foundation for Mental Health, 1970 December (Box 7)
  - Seessel, Thomas -- "Three Experiments in Shared Philanthropy" (folder 2), 1970 December (Box 7)
  - Talbot, Allan -- "Settling Things: Six Cases in Environmental Mediation", circa 1970 (Box 7)
  - Zimmerman, Stanley, Walter Farr and Lyle Marshall -- "New Enterprise in the Motor City - An Assessment of the Inner-City Business Improvement Forum of Detroit", 1970 December (Box 7)
  - Zimmerman, Stanley, Walter Farr and Lyle Marshall -- "New Enterprise in the Motor City" (folder 2), 1970 (Box 7)
  - Zimmerman, Stanley and Walter Farr -- "Their Business is to Help Business" Re: National Council for Equal Business Opportunity (NCEBO) and Baltimore's Local Council, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Newman, Jon -- "The Levitan Approach - Assessment of a Grant to George Washington University for its Center for Manpower Policy Studies", 1971 March (Box 7)
  - Rezendes, Dennis and Thomas Seessel -- "R+D+NYC=C - Assessment of a Grant to the New York City-Rand Institute", 1971 November (Box 7)
  - Clemow, Bice -- "The Fallowing Years - An Assessment of the John F. Kennedy Institute", 1972 January (Box 7)
  - Manning, Robert and Arnold Spellum -- "Two Organizations, Two Approaches, One Objective" Re: Grants to Capital Formation, Inc. and the Chicago Economic Development Corporation, 1972 April (Box 7)
  - Quick, Charles -- "The Students Deserve Better" Re: Grant to Texas Southern University to Educate Black Lawyers, 1972 April (Box 7)
  - Deutch, John -- "Whither These Resources?" Re: Resources for the Future, 1973 February (Box 7)
  - Feldstein, Lewis -- "Now That We Are Beautiful, Where Do We Go? Assessment of Grants to the American Jewish Committee for the National Project on Ethnic America..." (folder 1), 1974 February (Box 7)
  - Feldstein, Lewis -- "Now That We Are Beautiful, Where Do We Go?" -- Draft (folder 2), 1974 (Box 7)
  - Talbot, Allan and Robert Goldmann -- Report Re: Interviews Conducted with Economists Re: Program Development at Ford Foundation, 1976 (Box 7)
  - "Summaries of a Series of Welfare Policy Papers", 1977 (Box 7)
  - De Silva, C.R. -- "Sinhala-Tamil Ethnic Rivalry and the New Constitution of Sri Lanka (1978)" (Box 7)
  - Jackson, C. Ian, Harvey D. Shapiro and Ronald Stegall -- "CIUL, NAULO, and IUTEP: An Evaluation", 1978 March 31 (Box 7)
  - Jackson, Shapiro, Stegall -- "When Better Mousetraps Are Built - A Report to the German Marshall Fund and the Ford Foundation on Efforts to Facilitate the International Exchange of Urban Ideas", 1978 July (Box 7)
  - Goldmann, Robert -- Summary Drafts of Conference on Two World Cities: New York and Paris Re: Urban Policy, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Sviridoff, Mitchell -- "The Social Pathology of the Ghetto" -- A Paper for the Conference on Two World Cities: New York and Paris (May 24-27, 1978) (Box 7)
  - Ford Foundation Concept Papers -- Drafts (and correspondence) -- Human Rights and Justice, Ethnic Conflict, Education, Governance and Public Policy, Youth, Urban Poverty and the Disadvantaged, Resources and Development, Communities and Neighborhoods (folder 1), 1978-1981 (Box 7)
  - Ford Foundation Concept Papers -- Drafts (and correspondence) -- Human Rights and Justice, Ethnic Conflict, Education, Governance and Public Policy, Youth, Urban Poverty and the Disadvantaged, Resources and Development, Communities and Neighborhoods (folder 2), 1978-1981 (Box 7)
  - Alschuler, John -- "Community Energy Strategies: A Preliminary Review" (folder 1), 1980 August (Box 8)
  - Alschuler, John -- "Community Energy Strategies: A Preliminary Review" (folder 2), 1980 August (Box 8)
  - Goldmann, Robert -- "Report on Israel-VI", 1981 September (Box 8)
  - Srinivasavaradan, T.C.A. -- "Constitutional and Administrative Institutions Relevant in the Context of 'Ethnic' Tensions in India", undated (Box 8)
  - "Outline for Selection and Treatment of a Series of Case Studies in Dispute Resolution", undated (Box 8)
  - Card Catalog (notecards) of Project Evaluations Written/In Progress, 1968-1980 (Box 8)